<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvvere to the question: vvhether the Emperour that now is, can bee iudge in the Bohemian controuersie or no? Together with the extract taken out of the acts of the Dyet at Auspurghe, in the yeare 1584: concerning the kingdome of Bohemia.</title>
            <title>Antwort auff die Frage: ob der jetzige Käiser in der strittigen Böhemischer Sachen Richter sein könne oder nicht. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00675</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101960</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837763</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837763</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2103</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00675)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2103)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvvere to the question: vvhether the Emperour that now is, can bee iudge in the Bohemian controuersie or no? Together with the extract taken out of the acts of the Dyet at Auspurghe, in the yeare 1584: concerning the kingdome of Bohemia.</title>
                  <title>Antwort auff die Frage: ob der jetzige Käiser in der strittigen Böhemischer Sachen Richter sein könne oder nicht. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Jones? or W. Stansby?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.C.XX. [1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Probably a translation of "Antwort auff die Frage: ob der jetzige Käiser in der strittigen Böhemischer Sachen Richter sein könne oder nicht", published the same year.</note>
                  <note>The Diet of Augsburg in fact took place in 1548.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D²  (-A1, D2).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ferdinand --  II, --  Holy Roman Emperor, 1578-1637.</term>
               <term>Bohemia (Czech Republic) --  History --  1526-  --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2103:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2103:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWERE TO THE QVESTION: Whether the Emperour that now is, can bee Iudge in the BOHEMIAN Controuerſie or no?</p>
            <p>Together with the Extract taken out of the Acts of the Dyet at Auſpurghe, in the yeare 1584: Concerning the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M. D. C. XX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:2103:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2103:2"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to the Queſtion; whether the Emperour that now is, can be Iudge in the Bohemian Controuerſie or no? To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Extract taken out of the Acts of the Dyet at Augſpurghe, in the yeare 1548: concerning the Kingdome of Bohemia.</head>
            <p>THey that endeuour to attribute vnto the Imperiall Maieſtie that now is, the office of a Iudge in the Bohemian Controuerſie, ground their opinion vpon this, that namely, the Crowne of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia is an Electorate &amp; a Fee depending on the Empire; from whence they inferre, that as it is onely and alone due vnto a Roman Emperour to conferre Electorates and Fees depending on the Empire, ſo likewiſe it is due onely and alone to the Emperour to iudge and to giue ſentence in and of the ſame; and, that in caſe of not obeying or gain-ſaying, he may make vſe of his Imperiall authoritie.</p>
            <p>But whilſt the King of Bohemia that now is, being beſides Count Palatine and Elector, hath accepted of that now mentioned Crowne, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorate and Fee imperiall; and that at that time when his Imperiall Maieſtie was exalted vnto the Imperiall dignitie, was of the ſaid King himſelfe acknowledged to be his Emperour, and
<pb facs="tcp:2103:3"/>liege Lord; and knew verie well that his imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Maieſtie laid claime to the ſaid Crowne, Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorate and imperiall Fee: hauing beſides that neglected the reſpect he oweth to his Imperiall Maieſtle, as well in not abandoning that once accepted Crown according vnto the monitoriall Mandate ſent forth in that behalfe; as alſo in not obeying (as hee ought) his lawfully ordayned Emperour, and liege Lord.</p>
            <p>And therefore his Imperiall Maieſtie, beeing lawfully elected Emperour of the Romans, and Lord of the ſaid Fee, and ſo ſupreme Iudge, can and may vſe againſt the ſaid King all ſharpe, conſtraint, and executionall proceſſes.</p>
            <p>But euerie one (the eyes of whoſe vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding are not altogether blinded with ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming affects) can caſily perceiue the inſufficiency of thoſe confuſed arguments, if he vouchſafe but as it were by the way to conſider and looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon both parties, and vpon the cauſe it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>For it is more then world-notorious, and more then manifeſt out of all Writings, edictall caſſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Mandate ſet forth and publiſhed by his Imperiall Maleſtie, that his Maieſtie neither pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth nor groundeth his complaint vpon any wrong done to the holy Roman Empire, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting of the ſaid Crowne of Bohemia: But al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together and alone vpon this, that namely the mentioned Crowne of Bohemia appertayneth onely and alone vnto the Houſe of Auſtria, as being an onely Inheritance of the ſame; and that
<pb facs="tcp:2103:3"/>therefore it is due vnto his Imperiall Maieſtie, as being borne an Archduke of Auſtria.</p>
            <p>But if his Imperiall Maieſtie may lawfully ground his claime of his pretended inheritance to the Crowne of Bohemia vpon vertue of his obtained election to the Imperiall Dignitie, why then ſhould not the ſucceeding and from other Families deſcending and iſſuing Emperors, haue the like pretence and claime of Inheritance to the ſame Crowne? the which the Houſe of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria I am ſure would neuer allow of.</p>
            <p>It muſt therefore needes follow, firſt that the King of Bohemia that now is, hath nothing at all to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teſt with the holy Empire, nor with his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Maieſtie as with an elected Emperour of the Romans, touching the accepting of the Crowne of Bohemia now complained of, but as with a borne Archduke; and then, that his Imperiall Maieſtie in this priuate cauſe and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriacall pretence, nor ought nor can be both partie and Iudge, eſpecially whilſt the Kingdome of Bohemia alloweth no iuriſdiction at all to the Roman Emperour (ſaue onely in that which is due vnto the Empire, as from a Fee depending on the ſame.) And is not ſubiect neyther to the Roman Emperour, nor to the iudgements of the holy Empire, whether they be pronounced at the Imperial Court, or at the Chamber at Spire; nor to the Conſtitutions of the Empire, nor to the deciſions of the deuiſions of the Empire, nor to common acts of the ſame.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2103:4"/>
            <p>And whereas his Imperiall Maieſtie in this caſe againſt the perſon of the Count Palatine Elector, now King of Bohemia, will be conſidered and produced not as a partie, but as a Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, liege Lord and Iudge, it is more then ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurde; foraſmuch as his Imperiall Maieſtie it ſelfe in this Bohemian Controuerſie, hath neuer but intituled himſelfe King of Bohemia, and Tenant to the Empire, in that he ſtill hath endeuoured to confirme his pretence principally with this, that namely his Maieſtie hath beene inueſted into the ſaid and often mentioned Crowne of Bohemia, by a Roman Emperour.</p>
            <p>Wherefore then the Count Palatine Elector, and now King of Bohemia, can be in no manner accuſed as if he had committed any thing againſt the holy Roman Empire, and the Roman Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour his liege Lord, and ſo loſt that Fee of the Empire he hath accepted of.</p>
            <p>And if his Imperiall Maieſtie would needes herein ſupply the office of a Iudge as Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and liege Lord, then muſt he neceſſarily take vpon him two ſenerall and diſtinct perſons, and ſet the one vpon the imperiall Tribunall, and make the other as ARchduke of Auſtria, together with the Count Palatine Elector, to appeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and then iudge which of thoſe two hath the better Law, whether the Archduke which by clancularie Conuentions hath ſought to change and conuey the Crowne of Bohemia (a Fee of the holy Roman Empire) to the great diſaduantage
<pb facs="tcp:2103:4"/>and hurt of the ſame Empire, to the Houſe of Spaine, which long ſince hath affected an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Monarchy: or the Count Palatine, which ſtill hath, and as yet laboureth daily to obtaine the ſaid Crowne and Imperiall Fee from the Empire.</p>
            <p>And yet more abſurde is this, that they goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to perſwade the World as if the Count Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine Elector had done too much, and had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt the Law in accepting of that him offered Bohemian election and Crowne, and that at that time, when his Imperiall Maieſtie was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie exalted to the Imperiall dignitie: when his Imperiall Maieſtie was acknowledged by the ſaid Count Palatine Elector himſelfe, to bee his Emperour, and liege Lord: and when hee knew full well that his Imperiall Maieſtie laid claime to the ſame Crowne. For ſhould the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and reſpect of Imperiall dignitie be holden ſufficient enough for to barre him from accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of that, vnto the accepting whereof (as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly he beleeueth) he was warranted by God, and by the Law?</p>
            <p>And what will the effect of this obiection bee elſe, but to conclude that the pretence of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandant muſt needes bee the ſtronger in Law, becauſe he is now preferred to higher dignitie then he was before? There is no Prince of the Empire, which pretendeth not ſome one action or another againſt his equall in priuate affaires: But if his equall ſhould attaine to the Imperiall
<pb facs="tcp:2103:5"/>dignity, would that ſame his preferment be cauſe enough for to cut off the lawfull action of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prince? Or ſhould a Canon be barred from proſecuting his action he hath entred againſt his fellow Canon, concerning ſome priuate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, becauſe his fellow Canon and aduerſary is choſen to weare the Myter? Should a Citizen loſe his Law and pretence, becauſe his fellow Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen and aduerſarie hath got the Majorſhip? Should a Souldier giue ouer his ſuite, becauſe his fellow Souldier hath got the Captainſhip, and ſo a commaund ouer him that ſued? If wee ſhould graunt this, then muſt we likewiſe and moſt neceſſarily graunt, that the Dignities of what degree ſoeuer, haue beene brought in ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ſuppreſſion then for promotion of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: notwithſtanding the ſcope and principall cauſe of the eſtabliſhing and ordaining of heads, and gouernors in all eſtates and degrees of the World, is, that thereby good gouernment may be maintained, Law and Iuſtice may be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to euery one which ſeeketh for it, and to whom it is due; and that none may be moleſted by another vnlawfully and wrongfully.</p>
            <p>And although in all eſtates and degrees, euery one is bound by Law and Iuſtice to render due honour and reſpect to his lawfull Superiors, yet ought that ſame honour and reſpect to be in no wiſe derogatorie to the right of him that is bound to honour his Superior, but rather a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and way to attaine to the ſame.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:2103:5"/>
            <p>But more then abſurd it is that they dare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade his Imperiall Maieſtie to make vſe of his obtayned Imperiall power for to maintaine and colour his priuate Auſtriacall pretence, and to goe through-ſtitch with force, as being Roman Emperour: witneſſe all thoſe Writings and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents which here and there haue beene publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and putſorth vnder the name of his Imperiall Maieſtie, concerning as well the forcible Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Armie rayſed in the Prouinces of Lower Burgundie, as alſo thoſe which are and haue been entertayned of the vnited Electors, Princes, and Eſtates of the Roman Catholique Religion. For in the ſaid Writings there be contayned theſe two reaſons, That (namely) theſe Armies haue beene leuyed; firſt for the maintenance of his Imperiall authoritie; ſecondly, for the recupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame, as which hath beene taken away from him and from his Houſe of Auſtria, in and together with Bohemia.</p>
            <p>Out of the which reaſons euery one may eaſily perceiue, to what end the pretended firſt reaſon, which is the Imperiall authoritie, ſerueth; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that vnder the Cloke of the former, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond reaſon, which is the claime of Auſtriacall intereſt, might be the better put forward: which is indeed a moſt monſtrous and great abuſe of Imperiall authoritie; foraſmuch as it is moſt manifeſtly proued and euident, not onely out of the Conſtitutions of the Empire, and all Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Capitulations, but alſo out of Nature, that
<pb facs="tcp:2103:6"/>the Imperiall authoritie is giuen to all and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Emperour, to this end onely, that right and iuſtice (the onely true foundations and Pillars of euery Realme, and without which no Realme can nor may ſubſiſt) may be adminiſtred without partiallitie, no Prince and Eſtate of the Empire moleſted. But euerie one, as members of one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, againſt all vnlawfull power defended, and ſo the whole Bodie in good vnitie, peace, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate preſerued: which end to obtaine, it would be impoſſible, if euery Prince, after he is exalted to the Empire, ſhould be allowed to confound the priuate actions of his owne or of his Family, againſt his or their equalls with thoſe of the holy Empire; and to driue through by war, proſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or other ſuch like ſharpe meanes (though they were made without all lawfull precedent cognition, and reſted onely vpon his owne will and pleaſure) that, which in <hi>propria cauſa,</hi> he neuer was able to performe and obtaine by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and that vnder colour of Imperiall Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigntie and authority: which indeed is nothing elſe but to ſet into diſquietneſſe and combuſtion and extreame danger, the holy Empire; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Imperiall Maieſtie that now is, hath highly obliged himſelfe to the encreaſing of the peaceable welfare of the ſame.</p>
            <p>But for to preuent and to auert all miſchiefe and inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience which might arriue out of the abuſe of the Imperiall authoritie, it hath beene moſt wholeſomely prouided by all the holy Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb facs="tcp:2103:6"/>Empire, that euery new elected Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſhall at his Imperiall election inſtantly be vrged by the electorall Colledge, to confirm and ratifie with a corporall oath this of ſo many ſtrong clauſes conſiſting imperiall capitulation: That namely, neither he himſelfe wil by violence and power, hurt or ſuppreſſe any of the Electors, Princes, Prelates, Counts, Lords, and other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of the Empire; neyther cauſe nor giue way to others for to doe the ſame: But if eyther he or any other hath to demaund any thing, be it of them all in generall, or of ſome of them in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, that then (for to auoid tumults, diſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and other hurtfull inconueniences in the Empire, and to preſerue peace and vnitie,) he ſhall open lawfull audience and proceſſe; and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in no wiſe, neyther in theſe nor in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, where they may haue ordinarie Lawes, and are willing to ſubmit themſelues thereunto, to hurt or to inuade by robberies, ſpoyling, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, defiance, warre, or any other way, vnder what colour, or pretence or name whatſoeuer: that he will and ſhall preuent and ſuffer that henceforth in no wiſe no bodie, be he of high or low degree, eyther Elector, or Prince, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without cauſe and vnheard to be proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or declared guiltie of iterate proſcription and baniſhment. But that herein all lawfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings and ordinances enacted by the holy Empire, ſhall, according vnto the direction of the reformed order of the Imperiall Chamber at
<pb facs="tcp:2103:7"/>Spire, be fully and ſtrictly obſerued and accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed: And finally, that he contrary vnto the golden Bull, and other Ordinances of the holy Empire, ſhall in no manner of way ſend forth, nor vſe, neyther of himſelfe, nor by way of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaty from other Magiſtates whatſoeuer, any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript, Mandate, or whatſoeuer may hurt; with this expreſſe addition, that, if any thing repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the aforeſaid poynts be eyther obtayned or ſent forth, then all the ſame ſhall be voyd and of none effect.</p>
            <p>Whileſt the now-Imperiall Maieſtie that now is, hath ratified and confirmed euery word of this Capitulation by a corporall Oath, it muſt needes be more cleare then the Sunne it ſelfe, that he neither ought nor can be both Party and Iudge in his owne proper cauſe againſt any Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor or Eſtate of the Empire, much leſſe make vſe of his Imperiall authoritie.</p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as it might eaſily happen that at one time or the other, eyther the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſhould haue occaſion vpon ſome contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie to enter action againſt one or the other Elector and Eſtate of the Empire, or ſome one E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector or Eſtate of the Empire, or the other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Roman Emperour, touching ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate cauſes and pretenſions; and that therefore neceſſitie would haue and require an vnpartiall Iudge, it is further expreſſely ſet downe and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned by the Conſtitutions of the Empire, and by the fundamentall Lawe of the Goulden Bull,
<pb facs="tcp:2103:7"/>that in ſuch like caſes, that is, when eyther the Roman Emperour ſhall ſue in Law any Eſtate of the Empire, or be ſued in Law by any Eſtate of the Empire; the whole matter of Controuerſie ought to be pleaded, and tried, and iudged one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and alone before and by the Count Palatine of the Rhyne, Elector, as ordinarie Iudge law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully thereunto authorized by and in ſtead of the whole Roman Empire.</p>
            <p>And although it cannot be denyed, but that, (for to giue ſome colourable ſhew to the abuſe of the Imperiall Soueraigntie and authoritie.) it is furthermore and againe alledged &amp; caſt abroad, becauſe this Controuerſie and Action concernes an whole Electorate of the holy Empire, that therefore all Electors together haue power gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto them, for to giue their iudgement, and to interpoſe themſelues in it: and that likewiſe not long ſince, with one conſent, it hath beene agreed vpon by the Electors to this end aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at Milheuſen, that namely his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie might lawfully, and by vertue of right and iuſtice, make vſe and put in vre his Imperiall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and power in this his Auſtriacall priuate pretence againſt the Count Palatine Elector, now King of Bohemia: yet is the ſame the verie fulneſſe and height of all abſurdities and vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſneſſes which euer were heard of vnder the cope of Heauen. For if the three ſpirituall Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors be of opinion that the Electorall Colledge hath power by reaſon of the Electorate of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,
<pb facs="tcp:2103:8"/>to take the cauſe in hand, and to iudge in and of the ſame, then had it beene their part and office at the laſt paſt Election-day at Frankford, when the whole Electorall Colledge was moſt earneſtly required, as well by the States of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia's Ambaſſadours, as alſo thereunto inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admoniſhed, by the Deputies of the three Temporall Electors themſelues, before all other things, to employ all their labour and paine for to appeaſe and take vp the matter, eſpecially <hi>cum Res adhuc eſſet integra.</hi> But whileſt at that time they would take no notice at all of it, whileſt alſo the Elector of Mogunce would not ſo much as once propoſe vnto the Electorall Councell-Table, the Letters of Intervention deliuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him by the Ambaſſadours of Bohemia, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his Electorall Grace ſhould haue done and performed the ſame <hi>ratione officij,</hi> as being Arch-Chancellor to the Empire:) whileſt alſo the three Spiritual Lords-Electors, together at that time would not permit the aforeſaid Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemian Ambaſſadours to come to that by them required audience, notwithſtanding it did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the Electorate of Bohemia, and was due vnto them by the verie Law Nationall; We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but greatly maruell, that now they ſhew themſelues to be poſſeſſed as it were with an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill before-hand priuily preiudicatiue conceyned iudgement; in that now, they of, &amp; among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and without priuity of the whole electoral Colledge, much leſſe of any other of the Princes
<pb facs="tcp:2103:8"/>and Eſtates of the Empire, ouer-ſhoote them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo farre, that, contrarie vnto all Lawes both diuine and humane, they forget not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne one partie vnheard, and to abſolue the other.</p>
            <p>Out of this manifeſt behauiour of theirs then, it will be hard to find out, or ſee any way, wherby they may or can be able to free the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialitie, much leſſe to ſhew or make, or obtrude themſelues Iudges vnpartiall; foraſmuch as it cannot be denyed but that the Crowne and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorate of Bohemia, hath his owne proper and vndoubted fundamentall Laws and priuiledges, according vnto the Tenour whereof, the King together with the Eſtates of Bohemia, ought to be conuented in caſes of the like nature, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth no iuriſdiction at all to the holy Empire, ſaue onely (as it was ſaid before) in that which is due vnto the Empire, as from a Fee thereon depending.</p>
            <p>And whereas the fault which was publiquely committed at Frankford, ſtriueth priuily and without all power to excuſe or ſhrub it ſelfe by and vnder the name of Imperiall authoritie; it is ſuch a thing which hereby muſt be remitted to the Iudgement and Tribunall of God, the moſt iuſt Iudge.</p>
            <p>But the things now ſpoken, are by no meanes to be thus vnderſtood, as if the King of Bohemia, Count Palatine, and Elector, would not ſubmit himſelfe, nor vndergoe any other lawfull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:2103:9"/>foraſmuch as he hath ſtill and of his owne accord offered himſelfe thereunto, if ſo be the ſame might be done and had in due and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient places, by vnpartiall and thereunto quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied perſons; but not before ſome few Eſtates of the Empire, arrogating vnto themſelues apart, and <hi>de facto ius iudicandi:</hi> Nor by his Imperiall Maieſties priuate Councel-Table, and obtrudent paſſionate Seruants.</p>
            <p>Neither is the queſtion which party hath the Law on his ſide, But whether his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, or his Priuie Counſellors, may or can be Iudges, or no? For, as concerning the meane and principall cauſe in and of it ſelfe, we referre the gentle Reader to the Deduction publiſhed not long ſince by the Eſtates of Bohemia, in the which there is contayned at large, firſt a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, how and in what manner they haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the right of their free Election, how and in what manner they haue continued the ſame without any interruption, till the time of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Maieſtie: Secondly, a fundamentall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of the Auſtriacal pretencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; grounds: Thirdly, a deductio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe moſt vrgent &amp; preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Motiues, by the which (aſſiſted by their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and well deduced right, and free Election) they were lawfully moued to reiect the Imperiall Maieſtie that now is, and to take in hand a new election: concerning which points they are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to giue reaſon, and anſwer in due place, and before competent Iudges; and to produce further
<pb facs="tcp:2103:9"/>proofe for to ſhew that their moſt gracious King and Lord that now is, is moſt vnkindly dealt withall, in that he is ſaid to haue pulled the Crowne of Bohemia from the head of his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Maieſtie, whereas his royall Maieſtie obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the ſame moſt lawfully by ordinarie and vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim free election, the ſame Crowne beeing then altogether vacant. But wee deeme it needeleſſe to dwell any longer vpon this, eſpecially diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as it were by the way, another groſſe abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie worthie to be taken away.</p>
            <p>For many there are found among theſe which entertaine an erronious opinion of the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the pretended clayme of inheritance of the Houſe of Auſtria, and which ſay, That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in the Golden Bull there be expreſſely reſerued vnto the Eſtates of Bohemia the right of free election, whereas in other temporall Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorates and maſculine Fees of the Empire, there is ſet down &amp; confirmed a ſpeciall order concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the hereditarie ſucceſſion in the ſame, of the eldeſt Sonnes and other neere kinſmen by the fathers ſide: that neuertheleſſe the ſame is to bee reſtrayned to the Family of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fourth, and ſo to the Houſe of Auſtria onely, foraſmuch as it is not to be preſumed that <hi>Charles</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and they then aſſembled Electors, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Eſtates of the Empire, would haue thus eaſily, and that directly giuen the Electoral office annexed to the Crowne of Bohemia, to the free election of the Eſtates of Bohemia, and ſo attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted
<pb facs="tcp:2103:10"/>the ſame to an vncertaine Family.</p>
            <p>But this imaginarie obiection hath as little ground and ſtrength, as may be found in this which would perſwade vs that the free Election of the three Cathedrall Chapters, of Mogunce, Colen, and Triers, of their Archbiſhops and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Empire, is not graunted vnto them ſimply, but is reſtrained to ſome certaine Houſes and Families: Whereas much the more it is to be preſumed, that, becauſe and whilſt, according to the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>den Bul, the other three temporal E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorates and Fees maſculine, cannot heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily deſcend vpon the daughters, but vnto the ſonnes onely, and to the neereſt kinſmen of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſide; ſo in like manner the Eſtates of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, after the Crowne of Bohemia hath bin made an Electorate, ſhould elect no woman to be their Queene, and ſo an Electrize of the Empire; as alſo the aforeſaid three Spirituall Chapters vſe not to chuſe women to bee their Archbiſhops, and Electors of the Empire.</p>
            <p>And ſurely it is a thing very new, nay hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neuer heard of in the holy Empire, that men ſhould ſo much haue endeuoured to appropriate the Electorate of Bohemia, as well to women as to men, and that by a fayned and neuer as yet proued right of Inheritance; yea, that the claime of Inheritance, pretended by his Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, will needes and principally bee deduced from a Woman, to wit, from <hi>Anna,</hi> wife to <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand</hi> the firſt, Emperour. Foraſmuch, as long
<pb facs="tcp:2103:10"/>as the Electorall Colledge hath beene, neuer wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man wore the Electorall office.</p>
            <p>And it would be a thing vnaccuſtomed and ſtrange, if a woman ſhould be either receiued or intruded into the Electorall Colledge, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that a woman is not onely vncapable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of by reaſon of the qualitie of that Sexe, as being vnable to accompliſh the warlike ſeruice due of ſuch Fee of the Empire to the Empire; but alſo that it would be reſembling more a Stage-play, then be conuenient to the grauitie of an Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Colledge, if a woman at the election of a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Emperour, ſhould ſit in the middeſt of the ſpirituall and temporall Electors, ſhould more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer ride together with &amp; amongſt them, ſhould performe the Electorall office, ſhould beare the Electorall ſword.</p>
            <p>Whereupon then now, and to conclude, it is left to the wiſe conſideration of the whole impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall World, but eſpecially of the moſt illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Electors, Princes, and Eſtates of the Empire, to iudge, whether it would be iuſt and lawful, and not rather contrarie and repugnant to God, and to the libertie of the Electors, Princes, &amp; Eſtates, if it ſhould fall out that his Imperiall Maieſtie ſhould, as well in this preſent caſe, as in other of the like nature, (where nothing at all is attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nor medled againſt &amp; with the holy Empire, nor any orderly and lawfull cognition had) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and maintaine his priuate pretence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt (the which by armes he hath defended ere
<pb facs="tcp:2103:11"/>and before he attayned to the Empire) by way of obtayned Imperial authoritie, and that againſt ſo chiefe an Elector of the Empire; ſhould in <hi>cauſa propria</hi> preſſe forward with Imperial pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſhould raiſe dangerous warre, not onely in Bohemia, the pretence whereof is controuerted, but in the verie middeſt of the holy Empire, and that by Spaniſh ſeruants, euill affecting the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Nation; ſhould be both partie and Iudge, ſhould as elected Roman Emperour adiudge to himſelfe ſuch pretended Auſtriacall right, ſhould condemne the contrarie part and that vnheard, ſhould put forth and execute the threatned pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of proſcription, and that vnder the name of Imperiall Soueraigntie: but for priuate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, ſhould by ſuch extreames expoſe to vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt danger of totall ruine (which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) the whole Roman Empire our natiue Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and that all contrarie vnto that by corporall oath ratified Imperiall Capitulation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus now (curteous Reader) haſt thou here a ſhort Anſwere to the propoſed Queſtion; Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame well, and deſire God to aſsiſt the right. Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:2103:11"/>
            <head>An Extract taken out of the Acte made at the Dyet at Wormes, in the yeare 1548: Concerning the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Bohemia.</head>
            <p>THe Royall Maieſtie of Bohemia, hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times and before this beene put in minde by his ordayned Councell of the Diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how that the King of Bohemia hath beene found in the laſt Contribution-Roll at Wormes, and that therefore the intent of the generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie of the Diuiſion, is, to put his Royall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie (as beeing King of Bohemia and Elector) likewiſe into the new Rolle, and to aſſigne him his portion of Contribution, for thoſe Landes which his Maieſtie holdeth from the Empire, as King of Bohemia, ſo as the ſaid Councell hath done alreadie in the reformed Contribution-Rolle.</p>
            <p>But becauſe this their motion and intent hath beene altogether ſtrange to his Royall Maieſtie, by reaſon that his Maieſtie heretofore neuer heard nor knew any thing of it; his Royall Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie hath deferred the matter (for want of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent preſent inſtruction) vntill his happy returne into the Crowne of Bohemia, where, after moſt diligent ſearch and enquirie made, he could find out or know nothing elſe, but that the Eſtates of the Crowne of Bohemia, knew of no contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:2103:12"/>to the Empire; and ſay plainely, that neyther the alledged Rolles of Wormes, nor the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter, hath beene made with will and conſent of his Royall Maieſties renowned Predeceſſours, Kings of Bohemia; and that they were neuer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to any ayde, nor neuer gaue ayde; and, in a word, that they owe none.</p>
            <p>Neyther can his Royall Maieſtie call to mind, that euer he was burthened with any Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or demanded any ayde; much leſſe payde or performed any, notwithſtanding not a few Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions and aydes to and for the Empire, haue beene made and agreed vpon by the Empire; Whereas, moreouer, the King of Bohemia is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſummoned to appeare or to be preſent at the generall Dyet of the Empire, and hath ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place nor voyce in the Councell of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, whileſt the Contributions to the Empire haue hitherto beene layd onely and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone vpon thoſe Eſtates which are contained and particularly ſet downe in the tenne Diuiſions. But the Crowne of Bohemia being found in no Diuiſion at all, the generall Eſtates of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire may eaſily perceiue and know that that Crowne hath heretofore neuer contributed with the Empire, and can therefore not be but wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully put into the Rolle of Contribution.</p>
            <p>Neyther doe the Contributions of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire concerne but onely the Eſtates of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire of the Germaine Nation, which reſt vnder
<pb facs="tcp:2103:12"/>the defence and protection of the holy Empire, and vſe the peace and Lawes of it.</p>
            <p>And though his Royall Maieſtie, as King of Bohemia, holdeth of the holy Empire certayne Countries and Dominions that vſe the German Language, yet haue the ſaid Countries and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, from the Romane Empire, neyther de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence nor protection, nor peace nor Law, but are from ancient times ſeuered from the Empire of the Germane Nation, into a particular Realme and Nation, and are not incorporate to it, and therefore not ſubiect vnto the burthens, aydes, and Contributions of the Empire of the German Nation.</p>
            <p>And though many Strangers, and outlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Potentates, hold of the Imperiall Maieſtie and the holy Empire, many renowned Countries and Dominions, yet are they neuer burthened, or ſubiect, with or to any Contributions and Aydes to the Empire of the Germane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Whileſt then, now out of this it appeareth, that the King of Bohemia is not bound to the Contributions of the Empire, but wrongfully and by meere error, put into the Contribution-Rolle of Wormes, or perhaps into others more ancient, as his Royall Maieſtie, as King of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, doth aſſure himſelfe conſidently, and hopes that the generall Eſtates of the Empire will deſiſt from their intent and demaund, and burthen his Maieſtie no more, then were his
<pb facs="tcp:2103:13"/>Predeceſſors, Kings of Bohemia. And if his royall Maieſtie, as King of Bohemia, and Elector, can doe or ſhew any aſſiſtance to the holy Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, or elſe to the Eſtates of the German Nation, as well in generall as in particular, for the profit and common welfare, whether it be out of duty, or out of good will or friendſhip, his Royall Maieſtie offereth himſelfe hereby moſt willingly and friendly thereto: giuing likewiſe hereby notice vnto the generall Eſtates, That as hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Eſtates of his Royall Crowne of Bohemia, haue ſhewed themſelues moſt obedient, readie, and forward in all occaſions of any neceſſities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Infidels, ſo now and hereafter they will not want to performe the ſame at the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of their power.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2103:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
